when we think about the kind of
caterpillar to butterfly metamorphosis
inside the chrysalis it's not a
caterpillar or a butterfly it's goo
right and that goo phase that liminal
phase the caterpillar is actually dying
right because the caterpillar doesn't
just lose weight and grow wings if you
look at it the the caterpillar has a
genetic code to go gather parts right to
gather minerals and amino acids and
sugars that are going to then be
reassembled into a butterfly if the if
we were just looking at the caterpillar
and we didn't know it's gonna butterfly
and we were looking at its getting
bigger and it's eating everything and
it's not pollinating anything we would
predict that it eats itself into
extinction except at a certain point it
gets rich enough blood chemistry that it
triggers this movement into the
chrysalis it starts to dissolve it gets
reorganized at a you know amino acid
level into something that now pollinates
the plants that the caterpillar
decimated across these vast spaces and
helps the evolution of the whole system
the butterfly phase could not have been
predicted from the caterpillar phase and
the so if we look at capitalism and the
military industrial complex and all
those systems as gathering parts right
very much like the caterpillar was net
consumption very much like a fetuses in
utero the fetus couldn't go past 40
weeks 50 60 it dies and the mom dies but
also couldn't come out much earlier
because it wasn't ready to make a phase
shift it comes out when it first can it
has finally evolved to the place that it
can actually do breast milk rather than
get food from the umbilical cord
directly but it also comes out when it
has to there's a fairly narrow window of
transition the same is true for an
animal developing inside of an eggshell
right there's a finite amount of
resources and when it runs out it has to
emerge but that's also the first time
that it can emerge that system can
handle the transition so we see in
nature this kind of precedent that these
discrete and nonlinear phase shifts
because there's a curve of in utero and
then there's a shift and then there's a
curve outside but that discrete phase
shift have come through the birth canal
is different than either the phase
before after